

OLIVIER ELÉA

Ph.D. Student in pharmacoepidemiology

- @ elea35.olivier@gmail.com in eléa-olivier-411973203
- @ Elea.OLIVIER@gustaveroussy.fr
- **J** +33 7 82 22 16 58
- Paris, France

STRENGTHS

Curious | Motivated

Determined

SKILLS

Programmation:

Python | R | SAS | C

MatLab | Excel | PowerPoint

MTEX

Mathematics/Statistics:

Generalized linear models

Longitudinal and survival data

Inferential statistics

Risk and scoring

G-methods

LANGUAGES

French: Native

English: TOEIC: 940 (C1/B2)

PASSIONS

Travel (Languages

Sports

Creation

SUMMARY

As a PhD student in pharmacoepidemiology, the main aim of my research is to study the carcinogenic and/or anti-carcinogenic effects of drugs widely used in the population. My academic background includes a double degree: a diploma in applied mathematics and a master's degree in public health with a specialisation in pharmacoepidemiology. My aim is to make an active contribution to research and understanding the impact of drugs on public health. In the long term, I would like to apply causal inference approaches to improve our understanding in this area.

EXPERIENCES

Ph.D. Student in Pharmacoepidemiology | CESP Exposome and Heredity Team/Paris Saclay University

Sept, 2022 - Sept 2023

- Villeiuif, France
- Thesis title: Glucocorticoid use and risk cancers in large real-word databases.

Research internship in pharmacoepidemiology | CESP, Exposome and Heredity Team

March 2023 - Sept. 2023

- Villejuif, France
- Olivier E, (...), Hicks B, Cairat M. Use of systemic and topical glucocorticoids and risk of skin cancers in a prospective cohort of women. Article in preparation.
 - Tasks: writing the protocol, statistical analyses (SAS software) and writing the manuscript.
- · Cairat M, Olivier E, (...), Hicks B. Quality evaluation of previous studies on glucocorticoid use and risk of site-specific cancers: a systematic review. Article in preparation. Tasks: extraction of data and assessment of quality / risk of bias of included studies.

Research internship in statistics applied to the social sciences of health | CERMES3

iii June 2022 - August 2022

- Villejuif, France
- · McKinley C, Olivier E, Ward J. The Influence of Social Media and Institutional Trust on Vaccine Hesitancy in France: Examining Direct and Mediating Processes. Accepted in the Vaccines journal. https://doi.org/10. 3390/vaccines11081319.

Tasks: protocol writing, statistical analyses (R and Python software).

Company internship in biostatistics | EXYSTAT

i Jul. 2021 - Aug. 2021

- Malakoff, France
- Tasks: Data anonymisation, clinical trial phase studies, statistical study on the France Assos Santé VIVRE-COVID study, work on logistic regression and mixed models.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Student in Pharmacoepidemiology | CESP Exposome and Heredity Team/Paris Saclay University

Sept, 2022 - Sept 2023

- Villeiuif, France
- Thesis title: Glucocorticoid use and risk cancers in large real-word databases.

Master's degree in Clinical Pharmacology and Epidemiology option pharmaco-epidemiology | University of Rennes

Sept, 2022 - Sept 2023

- Rennes, France
- With highest honour (Rank 1/16)
- · Generalized linear models, longitudinal and survival data, advanced statistical methods in epidemiology, estimation principles in biostatistics.

University Exchange Budapest | University of Technology and Economics Feb. 2022 - June 2022 Budapest, Hungary Applied Mathematics Engineer | INSA Rennes **2021 - 2023** Rennes, France · Probability, stochastic models of dynamic systems, inferential statistics, risk and scoring, time series. L1-L2 MIASHS (Mathematics and computer science applied to the humanities and social sciences) | University of Rennes **2018 - 2020** Rennes, France · With highest honour Lycée | Assomption **2015 - 2018** Rennes, France • Baccalaureate, scientific. With highest honour **CAUSAL-RELATED ACTIVITIES** CAUSALab Courses **2023-2024** Online & in person • Target Trial Emulation (Boston, USA), Causalab scholarships for students awarded (June 2024). • CAUSALab Course: Causal Diagrams: Draw Your Assumptions Before Your Conclusions (Online) Introduction to Causal Inference Course for Health and Social Scientists | University of Leeds (UK) **ä** Jan 2024 Leeds, UK • Causal framework, DAGs, causal mediation analysis, G-methods,... • Dispensed by Peter Tennent Active membre of the causal inference working group | Centre for Epidemiology and Population Health (CESP) **ä** Jan 2024 Villejuif, France • I made a presentation on key concepts of causal inference • Co-chair a subgroup on g-methods for time-dependent analysis. Reading in progress Ongoing • The Book of Why (Judea Pearl) • Causal inference: What If (Miguel A. Hernan and James M. Robins) OTHER ACTIVITIES

Communication

- Poster presentation: "Use of Systemic and Topical Glucocorticoids and Risk of Skin Cancers in a Prospective Cohort of French Women", ISPE 2024 Conference (Aug. 2024, Berlin, Germany)
- · Co-direction of the Early Career Research Lunch (ECRL) group: Organization of monthly meetings, discussion facilitation, and event planning to support young researchers.

Mobility

· One-month research mobility at Queen's University Belfast, contributing to a systematic review on glucocorticoid use and cancer risk

Interests and Extra Activities

- · Competitive athletics: Middle-distance running and marathon preparation, fostering discipline and perseverance.
- Painting and creative arts: Personal project combining art and self-expression.
- · Science mediation: Interested in popularising science for the general public using visual tools such as digital drawings, comic strips, infographics and presentations.
- Adventure sports: kitesurfing, windsurfing, skiing, dance.